So,
oh, and,
Commissioner or, Alternate Commissioner Smith,
is not present.
We have one change in the order to the agenda.
I want to add
agenda item 9B,
which is a fiscal year
'twenty three-'twenty four budget request.
We've
received word.
We need to get that in to the town so that the, and have it approved,
so that the
Board of Selectmen and Board of Finance can begin working on the town
budget.
So, I'll make a motion to the effect that we add that, again, out of 9B
FY 'twenty three-'twenty four budget request.
I'll second. I have a second. Okay, I got a second.
I'll just ask for a show of hands. So, those in favor of motion signify by raising your right hand.
Okay,
motion carries unanimously.
Items
number
well, okay, item number four, approval of minutes.
Our last meeting was on 10/03/2023.
I'll give you
10/03/2022,
excuse me,
and I'll give you a moment to review those. They were distributed.
I hope you have
them
handy enough to review,
and then I'll ask for a motion to
approve those minutes
whenever you feel comfortable.
>> I'll make a motion to approve the minutes from the October 3 Inland Wetlands Watercourse Commission meeting.
I'll second that.
>> Okay, we've got a motion and second.
All in favor?
Well, no, let's do this by roll call.
Commissioner Larson.
Well, did have a couple of comments
before
Go ahead. Folk
>> there.
On
the first page,
the fourth little paragraph up from the bottom, says,
what
we can to preserve the length of the lake that should be the life of the lake.
Although we can preserve the length too.
Okay,
>> so substituting life for length in that sentence.
Anything else?
Nope, all I had.
>> Think them
none again, we'll proceed with the vote. Commissioner
>> Larson. Oh, hold on. A minute. There it was. I found page two. I knew I had that. So on
page three,
about halfway down where it starts, George Elliott spoke
about last month's report
in the cleanup of tires and wheels in the vernal pit.
I think we're looking for vernal pool there.
I think you're
right there.
Good catch.
That's it.
>> No, I'm ready to vote. Oh, that's all right. Going once, going twice.
Once again, Commissioner Morrison. Aye.
Commissioner Masky.
Aye.
And Commissioner Monroe.
>> And I also vote aye, so the motion carries four-zero-zero.
And I can close that.
Okay, items five, six, and seven are
not germane since there's no public, no new business, and no old business.
Item eight,
agent report enforcement
actions. You mentioned one thing about a permanent extension.
So, agent one.
I think we incorporated that in our regulations
as some
grandfathering
of it's complicated,
but
yeah.
Okay, yeah, so so much for two and five year permit. Yeah,
Okay.
Right.
I'll
make a note of that. We can work that out and maybe take it up at the next meeting.
Okay, it doesn't look like there's been any action on that permit.
So
Right. Yeah, that was the big piece.
Okay.
Any other questions about agent activities?
I had one. I wondered
if there's been any, action
on, let's see, it was permit
20.
It's on Lake Road, Lock 22,
the driveway
and culvert
installation.
Been in contact from the
permit holder for the for the applicant
or an engineer.
Yeah.
Uh-huh. Okay.
Okay.
I just wanna follow-up, like, as as commissioner Larson,
pointed out at
previous meetings,
there's sometimes a slip in terms of communication
on what gets done versus what gets approved.
Okay.
Well,
moving on then, we have, I see, Mr. Tuttle,
from Public Works Department on the call now.
And,
Item
9A on the agenda is discussion for policy
for projects in wetlands or upland review areas by public works, especially roadworks.
So, Mr. Tuttle, if you could give us a brief description
of what you're trying to accomplish here, of what you'd like the Commission to do to facilitate
your
work.
>> All right, good evening. Thanks for having me.
Yeah, I'm
come to you guys tonight for
discussion
tonight,
further meetings, you know, future meetings.
What can we do at Public Works
basically
to make it a little bit easier for routine maintenance
for
catch basins,
the water courses that immediately
enter
and exit
cross culverts.
Routine maintenance that needs to be done around
structures and the waterways
off the road, you know, the little ditch lines that go to
a culvert, things like that.
Is it
such a,
know, we got to present a plan for each and every one of these things, or can I just go along or we,
you know, as we're doing road work,
we need to do some maintenance,
and we just take care of what our needs are
within the towns right away?
>> Okay.
You mentioned I got a copy of your email,
to Agent Wagner
and forwarded that. You also mentioned,
specifically,
brush and tree woody plant maintenance
in
the vicinity,
as well as the, and
separately, kind of the hardware,
the hardscaping part of it, the
actual structures,
and as you say, the waterways that exist
on the town roadways, Right,
road rider
>> so
to that, I didn't get to that part yet, but,
you know,
for instance, I'm going to bring up the bridge
over the Hop River at Hendee.
So when the water levels down,
there's a
couple of
sandbars
or
whatever, just
areas where the
trees
growing underneath the bridge
or they're up against the wing walls
and
that stuff needs to be removed.
Otherwise, it's going to cause damage
as the trees grow bigger
to those structures.
Know, so and that stuff typically needs to be clear 25 feet away from the structures.
That's,
know, same thing with our catch basins.
We've got some old head walls that are stone.
You know, I've already had to do a couple of trees that were just about ready to be uprooted.
They are almost down anyway.
Can speak of
two trees on Townsend
at that cross culvert there.
You know, if the tree falls over and it takes the stone abutments out, you know, that's a problem. Yeah, but
it didn't affect, you know, that was an emergency thing, I had to get it done.
So I guess my question is,
what is the best way
that
at Public Works that we can accomplish these tasks
without
basically
making it,
it
puts these jobs off for
could be months at a time. I mean, it simple or just we have a policy and then I can call,
know, Joe, the inland wetland
agent and let them know what's going on. I know other towns do similar situations.
You know, may have a catch basin that's crumbling that we have to
rebuild.
You know, so it's simple
projects like that. I mean, I call them simple.
It's nothing more than
repairing,
replacing
maintenance of existing structures and
existing
waterways.
>> Okay.
Well,
thanks
for that. I'd like the
opportunity for commissioners
to ask questions or clarification
on this.
Obviously, we can't take any action on this tonight, but it
would require some
revision to policy or regulations
or both,
And I'll speak to that in a little bit, but first I want to get
again back to the Commissioners to see if anybody has any
questions
or concerns or comments
regarding,
again, your basic objective is to streamline the process for,
again, what we'll call for the sake of
discussion,
routine maintenance
and
repairs.
We could also perhaps look at emergency
repairs
and how we handle those.
So,
first of all, Commissioner Larson, do you have any questions,
comments?
>> Well,
an observation,
I
go back to,
I think it was a year or two ago that
Jeff Murray was
interested in pulling some branches out of, I think it's Chamberlain Pond. Yes.
And
it seemed like a pretty benign
thing to do,
but we concluded that
he could not do that without a permit, although if a private property owner
were doing that, he could. That was maintenance. But since it was
town work,
and that might not be the right term,
he had to go through
getting a permit
to pull branches
out of the out of the pond.
And
I'm
sort of in favor of streamlining
the process as Jay's talking about. I just
I didn't I didn't recall that until I was reading through the proposal trying to
think about different things and how that went there. So that was one concern. Are we precluded from doing that because our regulations
might prohibit it?
I guess the other thing that that would
is always a concern to me on
these different items
is,
you know,
have we identified the wetlands boundary or the upland review area boundary and where we're actually
adding that?
And that's probably,
I don't know if that's a holdover from previous,
not having it
done or not, but you would think you know it's always going to be maintenance on these
same kind of systems. We're always doing
the roadwork
in the same areas, so
it might be nice if you know and Jay, you know way in advance what you're going to be doing.
We could you know start building the portfolio
of
actually having the wetlands
delineated so that when we know
what
what you're asking to do, we can know whether it's in the wetlands itself
or in the Upland review area and that kind of thing.
>> Yeah,
if I may, Jed,
just make a quick comment.
So
that's not always the case that we know way in advance. Now I'm kind of speaking to
you know general routine maintenance.
Now
the project that we did last year and I'm going to speak to that a little bit over on Birch
not Birch,
Shottie Mill and
Birch.
So that was both
routine maintenance
and we had some improvements there.
So yeah, that was a project. There were some things where we added on, but ultimately
we didn't change anything
where the water courses
specifically
were
except for
we redirected.
I gotta shut my phones off.
Gotta keep my phones close by because you never know when you gotta get interrupted.
Anyway,
one specifically,
jeez, I forget the address. I think it was 21
down before
the rail trail,
the one where we redirected
the
outlet.
So,
that was due to the water was going in the person's backyard.
Sediment had built up so much over the years that it was going in the wrong direction.
And we find these situations
in many locations
as we're scraping the edges of the road,
doing the little waterways to where the water goes off the side of the road and leads to a cross culvert whatnot.
So these culverts,
some of them that are half full,
it's as simple of reestablishing
the
flow line
at flow line of the pipe, taking the sediment out, and then building a little plunge pool at the end of the pipe that we can maintain.
Ultimately,
that should be the goal for our department, public works.
We don't want sediment
or
things building up so much because we ignore them because it's difficult to get a job done.
And I don't mean to sound like
that's a problem,
but sometimes it's difficult for us to get things done.
And
maybe we put a blind eye to it. Well, we'll get to it someday when we have time.
But we really need to take action on some of these things
and this
the simpler things.
It's easy for me because I can just go in and do it because I know what I need to do.
If it's a matter of just reshaping that little
water course at the end of the pipe where it comes out so it flows like it's supposed to, like it was designed to do. Whoever built the road and the lay of the land years ago to make it go where it goes,
but now the sediments build up.
That's not a good thing.
Let me take care of it and move on. It's not always a
because a lot of those things we can do is we're going along cleaning our ditch lines.
You know, we take, I want to take the trees out away from head walls.
I want to open them up so I can see them as I'm driving by and inspecting them.
So it's
more of
a notification
that we're doing it. You know, I called or send Joe or the wetlands agent a note, say, hey, we're going to be working over here. And it's not like I'm affecting anything, but I'm working immediately right there.
Those are the kind of things that
I'm talking about.
Not so much a
full blown project like we did on Shotty Mill Road.
That's a little bit more in-depth.
Yes, it should have some review
questions asked,
but I'm
more
on the side of just routine maintenance.
>> Okay.
I'm certainly not opposed to that.
Know, the
first paragraph in the draft, and you know, it's a draft, talks about any repairs, maintenance, or replacement of structures or drainage systems.
Can be,
there's a significant difference between what that says in
pulling leaves and
trees that are growing
in sediment out of your
little pools.
You've designed it. I guess maybe one of the things you could do is
when
we approve a permit,
we could approve
restoring
it to design conditions
at your
discretion or something I don't know.
>> Yeah, mean if we if I come across a collapsed pipe
you know you
know let's
just say a 15 inches 18 inches pipe that's I'm not looking to change it. I just need to replace it. So that's a cross cover.
Couple days worth of work. We just dig it up and put in a new one. Fix the head walls,
know, ends of the pipe.
That's
is is that
is that something that we have to go for a permit or can it be just a notification
and we get the job done?
Because the per you know, if we're doing permit stuff like that, then then that that all takes time
And
it's kind of accumulative
of things.
>> I guess, you know, I'm looking for feedback from Joe or George on
the
Chamberlain
Pond analogy.
Were we too strict,
you know, in that? Or
how
does what Jay's asking for compared to that
one we went through?
>> I think your point was cogent. There is a little difference there. They were
asking to do activities
directly in a water course,
you know, not just around or
peripheral to, and it amounted to removal of material.
So it was pretty clear from our regulations
that that was a regulated activity.
Some of the things that Mr. Tuttle is talking about
might not necessarily
be regulated activities, or we could revise our regulations
to accommodate those kind of activities. I've got some examples from
Joe Wagner came up with some examples
from other towns that we can
take up in a minute.
But as I say, first, I wanted to get your immediate
reactions,
comments, concerns,
and
sort of to guide us in whether we think that this is an area where we could
make some headway in terms of
looking at how
we could accomplish
facilitating
that process
for public works projects.
So,
Jud, let me
give the other commissioners a chance to weigh in here.
Commissioner Mashke, did you have any
questions,
comments, concerns about
this sort of line of
inquiry here?
>> A question would be, and I'm new, so forgive me if this is, you know,
inappropriate, but I'm wondering,
could those,
so what you're
saying about the places that are regular maintenance,
could those places be identified?
Like, could you just, you know,
put a group of 20 different places where you'd like to not have to do a permit, but you could go in and regularly do those maintenance?
>> I mean, anything could be identified.
It
depends on,
you know, when you're going to do it. So if I identify 20 places and it takes me two years to get it done or three, you know, it just it's part of
you know, we do our routine maintenance
every year on the sides of our roads. So,
in anywhere there's a catch basin, anywhere there's a
cross culvert,
as we're going by,
we try to inspect them and
it might make, you know, specifically
the catch basin repairs.
Is there a list in my head of where we need to do catch basins?
Yes, there is. Those would be kind of projects, but sometimes
we just need to do a catch basin right away because it fell apart,
>> you know. And would you do that? I mean, you were saying something about if you had an emergency,
>> I don't think you would wait for a permit, correct? You would just I would note, I would make notification and we just got to go to it. But generally,
if we're doing a lot of catch basin repairs or a specific area,
people
would be notified
about it and it'd be,
would I have time to go through a whole permitting process and spend the time doing that and having meetings and
maybe,
>> you know, you would be wasting time. And I, I get it, you know, like you were saying on Hendi, I live off of Hendi, so I know exactly what you're talking about. Yep.
Me, if that's something that you're doing that you have to do or have to
review on a regular basis,
then that
that makes sense that you don't need a permit for that, that you could just
notify
this commission to say, Yep, we're going to be doing it. Or yes, we did do it, but not to have to go do a permanent every time.
>> And to me, it makes sense. Correct. I'm just trying to find a way that is works for all of us that I can streamline
the routine,
the simple
maintenance really. Mean, the Hendy Road going up the hill,
there's a whole bunch of cross culverts that need to be cleaned and you know, the pipes are almost full.
So, but that takes, you know, it's going to take some time and some coordination just to get that work done. Right.
But that's, that's
>> just a, that's just a waterway when it rains. That's why I was asking if you know, like if you can list that list the, you know, and
you know, just make a general list
that
you know, is agreed upon. As long as you're just doing maintenance and no major changes,
that those would
be excluded from needing a permit.
>> Yes,
those things, yeah, that's kind of what I'm asking for is, you know, but you know, is it gonna happen not every time, it just might be a phone call and say, hey, I gotta get this done,
you know, but it is a, you know, a cleaning
maintenance thing, not a change. Right.
>> No, I think that's a
good idea because obviously paperwork is
can take forever. It's time consuming.
You're right. Yeah.
No, that's the only thing I had to say.
Okay. Commissioner Monroe.
>> Oh, I I've been thinking about this, especially while you're talking about it.
The only thing I could see where there might be a problem without getting
a permit
is if there's
a homeowner or a landowner or
that complains about something that's being done and
there's no, like,
I don't know, permit to do it. I
guess that would be the only thing that I'd be concerned about.
I agree with what you were talking about with
Jan there. If if you
if you have hotspots
throughout town, which sounds like we do,
and you know what where they are, and you know you're gonna have a problem, and it's not on that somebody else's property,
I would think that
it would be reasonable
to expect the
crew to go out there and do it and not need a permit.
>> So the towns
and the state
and I can't speak to the statute at the moment, but
they do have a right to drain
and
to properties. Of course, we're not supposed to have any impact to them. You know, there's there's water
courses that were designed on these roads that go to somewhere.
We're not supposed to put additional
impact on those areas unless it's permitted and you know reviewed and whatnot, but the routine maintenance of those that exist,
you have a right to maintain those. You got to protect the public. The water has to go where it was designed to go.
So
again, it just
I hate, you know, I hate keeping repeating,
you know, that it's a simple thing,
but it's not.
It's, you know, and it's common sense you think would apply in a lot of things and
it's
it's kind of a what's sad to say is that there's a lot of lack of maintenance
and that that's difficult to work through when there's so much of it. And some of these things are just easy to do when we're going by. It's a few scoops here and there. It's a, you know, get the leaves out of the trench that are all piled up and make a plunge pool at the end so the sediment falls right there on the side of the road and not going into one's property.
It's
the little things.
Replacing a pipe, a couple of catch basins
that are crumbling,
that's routine.
It's when you start building new stuff, yeah, now you've got to have formal plans and you know things get this discussion.
>> What he was saying, sorry, what he was saying before about if it was on
some private property,
I mean, would think that
if you ever touch that person's property,
yes, it needs a permit,
know, but if it's something that happens every five years,
then, you know, it should probably be.
>> Yeah, well, all the water courses go to somebody's property.
They all lead into somebody's property.
And if there's a, you know, a pile of sediment that's right there off the side of the road, you know, I don't want that sediment going into that person's property. I want to capture it on my So,
if I can correct that easily right then and there,
you know, at the time that we're there, that's what I would like to do.
>> But currently,
would currently,
if you saw that that had happened, you see that someone's got a lot of sediment,
you would
currently, you would have to do a permit?
Correct.
Okay. Yep.
>> And
you know, it's a lot of a lot of times when there's something, you know, like that, I'll just go knock on the person's door and and I said, hey, there's a lot of sediment. I'll walk them out there. I did that on shotty mill
to the gentleman that had,
I call it the swoosh way where we moved everything off the edge of the road
to get the water. You know, that was quite entailed to get that done.
And he had a lot of sediment
in his property that was actually in the wetlands.
So, and we went in and removed that.
And basically, think we restored the
wetland, got rid of all that old old sediment.
Something like that, you're going in a little bit further than, you know, the town right yeah, it needs to be reviewed make sure we're doing the right thing knock on the person's door make sure and but
I want to try to prevent that right that's what I that's my goal.
>> What do you do with the sediment that you pull out of all these places?
>> We take it to our pit
and we have I'm we're
starting to build
a loan pile of dirty loan
so we can screen it and reuse it.
So the different materials that we
take off the sides of our roads, as long as there's no invasives in it, we're separating it from the
stuff that has invasives,
which we
do not want to put that back on the edge of the road.
We try to reuse it where we can
and get vegetation
back on the sides of our roads so we try to prevent the erosion.
>> I mean, I would be comfortable with a
semi
detailed list of all the things that you would like to do that
maybe,
you know, we expect to be done on a routine basis. I know every year
the vacuum truck comes down your Lake Road here and sucks all the muck out of all the
catch basins.
Yep. I would have never thought that that was something we needed a permit for.
It's just something
that you do and
I would have
liked to say and I'd actually thought about it in the past, but I hadn't and I just expected it to be done. That's
good. So I certainly
want to encourage more of that,
not less of it. I think by
approving those kinds of things,
you know, list
maybe
nothing more is needed than that.
Guess that would be between you and Joe to figure out
what Joe wants, but
I think it's a good thing to be done. We just need to know where does the sediment go so we're not just dumping it back in end over lake or something. No, no, no. And I know you're not doing that.
But
you know, I think we owe it to know what the basic process is. And then we say, yeah, just we expect you to go out and do those things.
>> Yeah.
How's your wife going?
Yeah. We've we've never had a permit for something like that.
Right, I was going to comment on that. I have that.
Yeah, I think that
the
couple of points that have arisen here.
One is, of course, the scope of work,
And it seems that we have to tread a line between
the kinds of activities,
Jay, you're talking about, where you're coming along, you're doing some cleanup, and you say, Oh, there's a situation there.
It will be
simple,
straightforward
if we just deal with it now, okay?
But at some point, that project is going to take some planning,
all right? You're going to have to back up. And looking at the permits that we've issued
for public works over the past few years, we have
the drainage
at
the intersection of Shawty Mill and Wales Road,
okay, that was adjacent to a wetland.
We permitted it, and it was the kind of project where you had to put some planning into it because you were going to be digging up a big section of road and replacing
a pipe, okay? It was not a trivial
matter.
We approved the
work on
Hop River
Bridge at Bunker Hill Road. Well, Ta'o, you know, that was an emergency situation.
Nobody anticipated
that that bridge was going to blow out,
and, you know, you had to do something. We gave you the permit to do that.
And then
there was the work on Shawty Mill and
Birch Lane that was, again, that you just alluded to. There was some serious planning that went into,
and the extent of the work went beyond the immediate
vicinity
of the roadway, and it involved
redirecting
water courses.
So, those are clearly
situations
where permits were in order,
it seems to me, and that, you know, that with the planning process that had to go into that,
the addition of a
permit application
wasn't a huge
burden.
No,
you know, driving along
Shawnee Mill and, you know, cleaning out the
drainways and come to a plunge pool that's, oh, how did that get so full?
Let's clean it out right now. That makes sense. And,
you know, we, I think, what I'm hearing from the commissioner is that
policy
and or
regulations
that would give you the latitude to do that without having to apply for a permit
makes perfectly good sense.
I
think that
we need to think about, you know, what the dividing line is, okay? If you're tearing up
a road to install
a new length of pipe?
Maybe,
you know, because that's one example you use. It would be, you know, a couple of days work,
and let's do it while we're
working in this area.
But, you know, thatbut certainly
projects like the, you know, the Shawnee Mill
improvements,
again, it seems to me that a permit would definitely be in order. And looking at the policies
and regulations
for
other towns, at least the Ledyard one and the Mansfield one that Joe had brought to my attention,
you know, they make that distinction.
The Ledyard regulation
says that you can do things like
appropriate measures to mitigate erosion,
maintenance drainage culverts and cleanouts the first 25 feet,
reopening a culvert discharge,
as well as emergency procedures determined by the mayor.
Well, we don't have one or a designated official.
Emergency work for the safety of town residents may be performed under the purview of the director of public works. A permit for the emergency work may be requested after the activity.
Okay? So, that's kind of what we did with
Bunker Hill Bridge. We weren't
forcing you to wait until we got through the process
to get to work on the situation,
and I don't think any reasonable person would want to do that.
So
the question then for
the Commission,
given the, again, a sense of general agreement on principle that you should be able to go ahead and do that kind of routine maintenance
without having to file a separate permit for every
activity,
but at the same time reserving the right to require a permit for
planned
activities
of a certain scope,
you know, we've got to figure out how to implement that. And you say we could do it partly through regulations,
which is the Mansfield approach.
We could do it
through our regulations,
which has the advantage of,
how shall I say it, giving it some permanence.
You know, if it's in the regulations,
it's clear cut.
Yeah. You would have that, you know, you would have certain
abilities as of right,
and nobody's going to change that
without
some effort.
Whereas policies, you know, can be
interpreted
differently.
There's a little more leeway with policy.
And again, given the size of the town,
the fact that we don't have, you know, a lot of people
working either for public works or for the land use and building departments,
we do need to streamline,
the process as much as we can.
So,
what I'd like to do at this point is to kind of take this under advisement,
look a little bit more at the policies,
you know, and thanks for providing,
Agent Wagner with more
examples
that we can look at,
so that we can then
draft a policy
or
regulations,
that will get us towards that
goal.
And we could certainly take that up at our next meeting. We can, you know, make sure that that's on the agenda.
If it's a change in the regulations,
it's going to take a little more time because,
well, we have to notify
the
Department of Energy and Environmental Protection.
We have to have a hearing
on any amendments
to our regulations.
But, you know, we'll try to to work this out. And I think,
Jenny, if you could come back to us too with
a more,
shall I say, fleshed out list
of, you know, things that you've done recently or that you may anticipate doing in the near future
that would fall under the kinds of activities that you think would be that
could be
permitted either as of right or as a standing policy.
>> Okay.
Yeah,
Just just to that quick and I hate to take up more of your time.
There there is one thing
we talked about the trees removing around abutments and whatnot.
Add well,
who knows if we're going get any deep freezes or
so. If the water levels are down
and you know, I've been looking at a few of our bridges and and whatnot. I try to keep up on that stuff.
And that Bunker Hill, not Bunker Hill, the Hendy Bridge
and
this is the
other one escapes me at the minute moment. But anyway,
there's some trees at the one on Hendy over the Hop River. I really do want to clear those out.
And if it's feasible for us to get down there,
I would like, you know, I don't know if I need to file a permit or anything. I would like to get that those done over the course of the winter.
You know, because getting down in there is
good when the ground's frozen and crunchy a little bit, we're not really disturbing anything and then we can get them up out, get, you know, everything out of there.
>> Right, this involves, I think this is
vegetation that's actually in the water course,
not just in the Upland area.
Yeah. You've got stuff that's in the channel as it were. Well, would be if the water level
>> rise. Yeah.
Yeah.
So
that's something that if
I need to file a permit or you can discuss it and
let me know.
But the other things
as far as,
you know, I got a few ideas in my head. Can certainly put a list together as we start going around and scraping our roads, because eventually we'll be doing a little bit of
some drainage maintenance.
>> Yeah,
off the top of my head, would say that under the current
circumstance,
under the current situation,
it would be a good idea for you to
apply for a permit
for the Hendy Road
clearance work because,
you know, as I read our regulations now,
you know, that
would not be an as of right activity. That's an activity that would require a permit. No,
that's one of the things we want to address. But as you say, it's going to take some time for us
to
either formulate a policy
and or
amend our regulations
to get us
to the point where we're
satisfied
that we've met
your needs
while
still adhering to the statutes and regulations
regarding activities
in watercourses
especially.
And, you know, some of this is, you know, clearly the
removal of vegetation in the upland review area. Joe can approve that, and I don't think we even need a particular
permit or policy
or permit for that kind of work. That should be something you could do as right. And
some of the other things you mentioned certainly seem reasonable
to do as if right.
But like I say, we have to come up with the dividing line between
what's as of right or
allowed by policy
versus what's going to require a permit.
Okay,
I'll get together with Joe.
>> Okay, yeah, do that. And as I say, we'll share that information
about other towns
so that we can, you know, I always like to work from worked examples
because that means that somebody else has done the really heavy work of figuring out how to make a policy
or
regulation,
to fit the needs.
Okay?
Go.
You know, that's an interesting way of approaching it. And I think that might,
yeah, I would definitely be interested in seeing, again, all the different alternatives that
have
been developed
to address. This is obviously a common need. I'm sure every
public works department director in the state of Connecticut
is faced with the issue
of,
you know, what do we do about wetlands permits?
You know, and clearly, as he said, at some point you're going to have to ask for permits for certain kinds of work.
But, you know, we've got to find a way to allow you
to do the work
that,
you know, immediately needs to be done.
Any other comments from commissioners?
Okay.
Well, then, again, pending
further information,
we'll make sure that this is on the agenda for our next meeting.
We may have some concrete proposals by that time
for, you know, again,
a means
to that end.
Really?
Okay?
>> Okay. Thank you. Yeah. Thank you for your time and presentation.
Let
you go on to your next item of business that you have to do.
Okay.
Have
>> a good night. Alright. Thank you. Okay.
So moving on then, we have the budget.
Again, we have to take action on this tonight because
it's due in town hall by the end of the week, I think.
And of course, we didn't have meetings in November and December, so we couldn't talk about it at that time.
The
budget proposal,
I
think I shared to you, I sent it around, I don't know if everybody got it, but I sent an email this afternoon
with a PDF
of the
current year budget
and
the expenditures
so far.
I'll
just quickly walk through.
Of course, the major item on the
budget is the
stipend fees
for the board clerk. Hooray. I'm so glad that we have a board clerk.
And I'm sure Joe is also very relieved not to be having to take minutes.
So,
the fact is that,
you know, I don't know if $14.50 is adequate. Normally we have about 10 meetings, you know, there's
12 regular meetings scheduled. We may have a couple
special
meetings, and then we'll probably have a couple of cancellations because we don't have any business.
So, you know, I have no idea,
and
I only hope that the $14.50
that we currently have budget is adequate.
And I know your services are shared with other land use departments, so I
figured that we could probably work it out
between us and the building department
as needed.
We have a little bit of money in there for training. Basically, that would cover
if,
well, if Agent Wagner or if any member of the Commission wanted to attend meetings or training sessions
relevant, for example, the
Connecticut Association
of
Conservation of Inland Wetlands and Conservation Commissions,
CACIWIC,
as it's known,
has an annual meeting,
and if members wanted to attend,
that would cover their
registration
and
mileage
for attendance.
The past couple of years, of course, those conferences
have been virtual,
which makes them less attractive
in terms of opportunities
for networking and professional
development.
So,
I don't know. I think we should maintain that line in the budget just in case,
in particular
for A. J. Wagner's
benefit
should he
have the opportunity
to
attend meetings of such like.
We have $65
in the budget
for, well, it's for membership in the Connecticut Association
of
Conservation Commission and Enlightenment
Commission, so
we'll continue with that.
And we have a line item for office supplies. Now, Agent Wagner suggested
to the town manager
that we could or town administrator that we could perhaps combine that budget,
with the,
building department because basically they share their
sharing office supplies as it is now. I don't know from a budgetary point whether it makes a good, makes sense to align part of it to one commission and another part to another commission.
That's beyond my purview,
as long as Joe can get the office supplies that he needs to do the job.
And I don't know whether it amounts to $250
worth or not.
Yeah, it is.
Printer paper, a couple of toner cartridges.
Yeah,
that's right. You have a lot of legal filings, don't you? You have to send out official,
correspondence.
So, in any event,
what I'll do, I'll make a motion to approve a budget request of
$19.65
dollars as
noted
in the provisional budget supplied by the TAB.
I'll second. Okay, so we got a motion and a second.
Any further discussion? Any ideas about
where money could be spent or where,
God forbid, money is not needed?
>> A couple of comments. One, I like Joe's idea of, having
the consolidated
office supplies thing. Think it must be kind of consolidated already.
I can't imagine
Joe having his own stash of pens and
paper down there.
>> I haven't, I noticed
we haven't spent any of that money so far this year, so you know.
Well, tell them if they need money, you can hit them up for you, okay?
>> I
think there was a comment
in the spreadsheet that came out with the budget that
for the board clerk
amount,
Eric was looking for
the number of meetings we expect to have in the average duration.
Then he would put in the figure
out the dollar
based on that. But he was looking for a number of meetings and
for planning and zoning, I put 15 meetings, two and a quarter hours each, you
know,
put in on that.
>> Yeah, I guess we could do that. We obviously,
it's quite
variable how much time we spend per meeting. This one tonight, I'm hoping will be fairly short and sweet. Sometimes we have more extensive But permit
yeah, we can certainly supply. As I say, a ballpark of about 12 meetings
should cover us,
maybe two hours a meeting on average.
>> Then the third comment I just wanted to make was,
and you're probably aware, but we do have a shared
pot of money with planning and zoning for
professional
and legal services.
So whenever
the Inland Wetlands uses the town engineer or
attorney branch,
that comes out of the planning and zoning budget.
It
is accounted for in there. I
think last year we went over a fair amount. This year,
from what I saw, we were
under budget so far, but we always have potential to
run up a bill at the last minute. Right.
Anyhow,
we should be aware that,
you know, that stuff is coming out of
I have to budget for that with planning and zoning. Okay.
>> Well, thanks for keeping us in mind, keeping this commission in mind as well when you formulate that budget.
Absolutely.
>> Yeah, Eric had explained to me that that was on, you know, I mean, obviously, the attorney's on retainer,
and then we have to pay
up by billable hours
when they are accrued.
Okay, so any other comments about the budget?
Okay,
seeing none, I'll ask for a vote on motion.
Commissioner Larson?
Aye.
>> Commissioner Mashke?
Yeah. Aye. And Commissioner Monroe?
Aye.
I also vote aye, so the motion carries four-zero.
Jed, I'll
convey this to
the administrative assistant,
you know, the budget request, and I will add that information about
time and
number
of meetings.
Okay.
Let me get my agenda back up on my screen.
Okay, yeah, we finished with the business.
Our next regular meeting is scheduled for
February 6, a Monday,
at 7PM,
same time, same place, and maybe even the same Zoom
address and everything. So,
with that,
I will entertain a motion for adjournment.
I second.
>> Okay.
We got a motion and second. No objection?
Without objection, then the meeting stands adjourned.
Thanks to
everybody. Happy New Year to you all. Look forward to
filling out our terms,
which end at the end of this fiscal year,
June
2023,
in good order
and with interesting
business to take care of.
That's good.
Thank you. You Have a nice
>> too. I
guess we're all permitted now to
click on the little red leave button in the lower right hand corner of your screen,
And again, I'll see you, Joe, of course, I'll be in touch with you about policy stuff. Good night, everybody.
Good night.